How's it going everyone? In this video,
we are going to be doing episode two of
my top- down chart lessons. In this
case, reviewing a trade from previous
week on the S&P 500. Let's get into the
example. You can see here on the daily
chart, we have an aggressive move lower
and an aggressive move higher. You can
tell this as we are generating fair
value gaps on both sides of the market.
We have an aggressive move lower and
then we have this other fair value gap
making an aggressive move higher. So
that's forming a V-shaped reversal. Now
if you look at a higher time frame, so
if we go to the weekly time frame here
after removing these drawings,
you'll notice when you have an
aggressive move lower and then back up,
that's forming a reversal candle on a
higher time frame. So with a reversal
candle here, I'm looking for price to
trade higher in this following week and
going to take out this previous high. So
going back to the daily chart, what do
we have? We have Monday open up as a
consolidation. And that makes sense
following a large expansion on Friday.
So with the closure near the low, if we
are going to frame a reversal or look
for this reversal day, where can I look
to trade that? Well, I can look for that
previous day low as I talked about in my
candle 2 video. Now marking out my point
of interest as a fair value gap. The
easier trade does lie in the
continuation. So looking for the
continuation following Tuesday reversal.
I'm looking for Wednesday to trade
higher. And that is the whole bias or
idea for this trade is Tuesday has
reversed. So looking for Wednesday to
continue in line with this trend as we
have expansion retracement into a fair
value gap. Looking for another
expansion. So what do I want to look for
next? Well, if you've watched my
playbook video, I want to go down to the
hourly chart. Down here on the hourly
chart, I want to confirm that reversal.
So, I'm going to go and find the
reversal point, which is this low. I'll
find the low. I'll look for the series
of down close candles that made that
low. And did we get a closure through
that level? And we did. So, now I'm
anticipating this reversal to be
confirmed and for the next candle to
trade higher. Now, where do I want to
see this candle trade higher from? Well,
I want to mark out 0.5 of this previous
candle. Now, for simplicity sake, I'm
going to go ahead and remove my drawings
and just leave on my indicator. So, you
can see we had a reversal Friday and
Monday, we didn't really get any action,
right? We just had a consolidation or
this slow shallow move. So, expansion,
is this a consolidation or a
retracement? Well, I view it as a
retracement. And then we do have a
reversal day. It's a bit tricky to try
to trade that. And that's why I say
continuations are much easier. So,
falling into this next day, where do I
want to see price respect? I want to see
it respect the upper half of this daily
candle because I want to see a small
shallow wick so we can expand higher.
That is where I'll be looking for a
point of interest or for price to
reverse out of. So, as we move ahead
into the New York session, you can see
we have these short-term targets as well
as that previous daily high or that
weekly high. And what are we doing into
this? Right, you can see we do have a
little reversal off previous day high.
This doesn't make sense for a bearish
perspective as we are just leaving these
failure swings here. So that is
basically irrelevant to me. And so
taking a look at this, this could be
considered a retracement. But I don't
really trust this. This is just a
consolidation. So if we are forming a
consolidation, what do we want to look
for? Well, we have the range high and
then we have the range low. So I want to
see the range low be taken out into a
point of interest. I have a fair value
gap here in the upper half of the
previous daily candle.
So, I want to see price form a reversal
in here.
Now, if you take a look, I know I want
to have this point of interest. Here is
a reversal candle. I can be looking to
trade this higher. Now, let's go over a
few things. We're going to go ahead and
go to the 4hour chart and expand out.
Now, why did I choose ES and not NQ as I
do prefer to trade in Q? Well, I looked
at YM. Generally YM is strongest, NQ is
weakest and then ES will be in the
middle or vice versa. But here when I
see that YM is very strong, I know that
NQ is the weakest pair. But if I'm
looking to trade long, I would prefer to
trade ES longs over NQ longs. So coming
back to ES here, that is the 4hour
chart. You can see we have this
reversal. And let's dig into this and
see how I got an entry. If we're down
here on the 5-minute chart, I'm looking
for price to reverse out of this range
low here and trade to the highs. That is
my whole idea. So, I'm looking for a
reversal in here. Now, you can see price
has a bearish reversal here on the 9:00
a.m. open. It does go to its max
expansion. And what do we have? An
aggressive move lower met with an
aggressive move higher. That's forming
this higher time frame wick. And I have
a change in the state of delivery. Now,
those of you that know my model and the
T-spot, you know I'm looking for certain
areas to respect here. If we are going
to form a higher time frame wick here, I
want to see.5 of this wick be respected.
And if I'm wanting to see this change in
the state of delivery be respected, if
I'm anticipating this low to hold, I
want to see.5 of that be respected. So,
overlapping those two or that, I know I
want to see price hold this area in
here. I'll go ahead and remove all the
drawings to clean it up. This is where
I'm looking for price to hold. Now, do I
have a point of interest in this area? I
do, right? I have a fair value gap right
here. So, that will be my point of
interest where if I'm looking to trade
this, I'm waiting for price to come back
into this area to trade it higher. Now,
why wouldn't I just take an entry right
here? Well, I want to be able to exit or
partial off before or at my short-term
targets. If I take an entry up here and
I have to allow price to trade into
there and respect 0.5 of this order
block, that is not giving me good
risk-to-reward. So, I'm going to wait
for price to retrace to give me an
entry. Now, I am trading the reversal
here, and that is because I do have a
lot of context, and I was confident in
my higher time frame bias. But
generally, I'm going to let this higher
time frame candle close and then trade
the 10:00 a.m. continuation.
So, what I did here is we had a very
aggressive move lower. Now, this is
where I could look to take a limit order
in here. Put my stop there and look to
trade to the high and that would give me
2 R and that is fine. Now, I still
wanted some extra confirmation or to
trade off of this continuation in here.
If I was going to wait for the 5minute
continuation, where would that have
formed? It would have formed right here.
And once again, I would not have proper
risk-to-reward to trade to these
short-term highs here. So, with that
idea in mind, I'm then going to refine
this entry. So, I went down to the
3minut in this area. And you can see
we're also balancing out that fair value
up in here. And I notice the same thing.
I'm waiting for this continuation in
here. I'm not really going to be able to
get good risk-to-reward to this high.
So, this is where I will rarely, and in
this case, I did refine it down to the 1
minute time frame. So, with this, I'm
going to look for a continuation out of
this area. And so, I want to see an
aggressive move lower met with an
aggressive move higher. So, let's see if
that occurs.
I was actually looking to get entry in
here. Just none of these candles were
convincing enough for me to take an
entry and put my stop on these current
lows.
And here you see we have expansion down
met with an expansion up. And so, what
is that forming? A higher time frame
wick. This closure through here forms a
protected low right here. So, now I can
anticipate this low to hold as we trade
to this high. So once again, can I get
proper risk-to-reward with that? Well,
no, I can't. So with that, I'm looking
for another continuation entry. I'm just
looking to seek continuations until the
risk-to-reward makes sense. I'm not
trying to force myself on a trade and
just extend my target because often if
you do do that, price may reverse off of
that level there. So what am I looking
for? If we have expansion, I'm looking
for a retracement to get a new expansion
or expansion, consolidation, a move
lower to then trade it higher. So, what
do I notice here? We get expansion and
then I'm looking for this to be a
retracement. Why? Because we retrace
into a fair value gap here. So, with
that idea in mind, I'm going to
fractalize what I did on the daily. This
is a reversal candle on the 1 minute,
right? So if this is a reversal candle,
I have all this context where I don't
want to see this low get taken. Want to
see 0.5 of this be respected here.
Right? This is where I need price to
form a low if I'm going to trade it
higher with my model. So in that case, I
went and just waited for price to
reverse in here on the 1 minute, put my
stop on that low. I gained entry right
on the break of the high actually. And
then I'm looking towards these highs on
the left or just over 4R. Now I did go
ahead and partial out at 2R and you'll
notice that in the executions but you
can see once we get the closure through
here then I'm expecting what low to hold
this low to hold. So now I really feel
protected with my stop even with that
type of entry. Now it is possible if I
did miss that entry to still take an
entry like this right on the retest as
long as it gives 2 R because I have a
protected low in a continuation here.
But let's see how this works out.
And you can see we go and trade to those
highs. Now for me, I got out of all my
position when we trailed it. I was
expecting it to trade a bit higher. We
got this consolidation. We broke out of
this high. And for me, if we are going
to have expansion, a consolidation, we
break. I want to see a retest and for
that to go. If I have a consolidation, a
break, and then push lower, I'm viewing
that as a reversal that can then trade
lower. And that's where I want to be out
of my position. But if you notice my
executions, I took off at 2 R. I took
off at highs and then I trailed my
position and I essentially got out at
the exact same point that I took profit
here. So my runner just didn't do
anything besides my last take-profit.
You can see we formed that little low
there. I get trailed out and then that
is the rest of the trade there. Price
does end up going to its final objective
if we come back out here on the hourly
chart. But I am fine with my position
and how I trailed it. And if you notice,
we did get quite the retracement back
into this area before it did occur. So
the main points, if we're going to
review this one more time before I end
the video, is going out to the daily
chart. If we're taking a look at the
daily chart, I'm looking at the phases
of price. I have expansion met with an
expansion, which is a reversal. So I'm
looking for a continuation out of that.
Monday, we have a consolidation. Tuesday
sweeps out Monday's consolidation,
forming a reversal. So I'm looking for
Wednesday to trade higher. When I go to
the hourly time frame, I'm looking for
price to trade out of where the upper
half of this daily range. As if price is
expanding, I want to see shallow
retracements. What do we get? We get
expansion consolidation. And if you
watch my consolidation video, I'm
looking to trade from the low and the
consolidation. Once we sweep out the low
and the consolidation, that is when I
then go and use my indicator on the
lower time frames, or in this case, the
5minut. And I'm looking for price to
form a low in here. So going back to
there, this we did form a reversal. So
I'm looking to trade that reversal. I
just had to adjust how I was going to
enter in here in terms of risk-to-reward
and placing my stop where I felt
comfortable. So I ended up getting entry
in here. And then I want to be able to
take profit at these highs as those are
the intraday highs. And if we are going
to not expand in this day, that's where
I'm expecting a retracement, right? So
that's where I want to be taking off
some of my position. And so if we let
this go, you can see we do get a little
retracement in here
before expanding higher. Right? So that
is what took me out and I'm fine with
that trade. I did miss this move here,
but I would prefer to that to have just
occurred on this expansion here. So
that's just part of the game. But if you
have any questions, be sure to leave
them in the comment section below and
I'll get to them when I can. Other than
that, I hope you have a great rest of
your day and I'll see you guys next
time. Have a good one.